<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>GitHub | Mike Nguyen</title>
    <link>https://mikenguyen.netlify.app/category/github/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://mikenguyen.netlify.app/category/github/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>GitHub</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Mike Nguyen 2023</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://mikenguyen.netlify.app/media/social_sharing_image.png</url>
      <title>GitHub</title>
      <link>https://mikenguyen.netlify.app/category/github/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Create your own package in R</title>
      <link>https://mikenguyen.netlify.app/post/create-your-own-package-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mikenguyen.netlify.app/post/create-your-own-package-in-r/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;from-.r-files-to-r-packages-a-game-changer-for-empirical-researchers&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;strong&gt;From .R Files to R Packages: A Game Changer for Empirical Researchers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.tenor.com/YZPnGuPeZv8AAAAd/coding.gif&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34; style=&#34;display: block; margin: auto;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hello, fellow data enthusiasts! Today, we’re going to embark on a journey that will take us from a scattered mess of .R files to the organized, efficient world of R packages. Why, you ask? Well, let me tell you a story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, I was just like you. I had a bunch of utility functions scattered across numerous .R files. Every time I needed a function I wrote months, weeks, or even days ago, I had to embark on a treasure hunt through my files. More often than not, I ended up re-writing the function because it was faster than searching for it. Sound familiar?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I finally decided it was time to take the next step and start wrapping all my utility functions into R packages. And let me tell you, it was a game-changer. Here’s why:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Efficiency:&lt;/strong&gt; Having your own R package can significantly speed up your workflow. Instead of re-writing the same functions over and over again, you can simply call them from your package. This not only saves time but also ensures consistency in your analyses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reproducibility:&lt;/strong&gt; Reproducibility is a cornerstone of good research. With an R package, you can ensure that your analyses are reproducible and transparent. This is especially important when collaborating with others or when your work is subject to peer review.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.redd.it/qkkqz6wsiox11.jpg&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34; style=&#34;display: block; margin: auto;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34; style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learning and Development:&lt;/strong&gt; Creating your own R package is a great way to deepen your understanding of R and programming principles. It encourages good practices such as writing clear, concise code and thorough documentation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.quickmeme.com/img/ea/ea3b264e0bf73802d8311049b216a708736c38f492a21aec265324d0c6e800b0.jpg&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34; style=&#34;display: block; margin: auto;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34; style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sharing and Collaboration:&lt;/strong&gt; R packages are an excellent way to share your work and collaborate with others. By making your code available as a package, you make it easy for others to use and build upon your work. This can lead to collaborations and advancements that you may not have achieved on your own.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://img.devrant.com/devrant/rant/r_2137728_nYacL.jpg&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34; style=&#34;display: block; margin: auto;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34; style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Career Advancement:&lt;/strong&gt; Having your own R package can be a significant feather in your cap professionally. It demonstrates your proficiency in R and your ability to create reusable, efficient code. This can be a great selling point in job interviews or grant applications.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Customization:&lt;/strong&gt; With your own R package, you can create functions tailored to your specific needs. For example, if you’re a marketing researcher, you might create a function that generates plots in the style required by the American Marketing Association, like this:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;#&amp;#39; @export
amatheme &amp;lt;- function() {
  ggplot2::theme_bw(base_size = 14, base_family = &amp;quot;serif&amp;quot;) + 
    ggplot2::theme(
      panel.grid.major = ggplot2::element_blank(),
      panel.grid.minor = ggplot2::element_blank(),
      panel.border = ggplot2::element_blank(),
      line = ggplot2::element_line(),
      text = ggplot2::element_text(),
      legend.title = ggplot2::element_text(size = ggplot2::rel(0.6), face = &amp;quot;bold&amp;quot;),
      legend.text = ggplot2::element_text(size = ggplot2::rel(0.6)),
      legend.background = ggplot2::element_rect(color = &amp;quot;black&amp;quot;),
      plot.title = ggplot2::element_text(
        size = ggplot2::rel(1.2),
        face = &amp;quot;bold&amp;quot;,
        hjust = 0.5,
        margin = ggplot2::margin(b = 15)
      ),
      plot.margin = ggplot2::unit(c(1, 1, 1, 1), &amp;quot;cm&amp;quot;),
      axis.line = ggplot2::element_line(colour = &amp;quot;black&amp;quot;, linewidth = 0.8),
      axis.ticks = ggplot2::element_line(),
      axis.title.x = ggplot2::element_text(size = ggplot2::rel(1.2), face = &amp;quot;bold&amp;quot;),
      axis.title.y = ggplot2::element_text(size = ggplot2::rel(1.2), face = &amp;quot;bold&amp;quot;),
      axis.text.y = ggplot2::element_text(size = ggplot2::rel(1)),
      axis.text.x = ggplot2::element_text(size = ggplot2::rel(1))
    )
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This function creates a custom ggplot2 theme that complies with the American Marketing Association style. With this function in your R package, you can easily generate plots that are ready for your next marketing paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the beauty of R packages is that they’re not just for marketing researchers. Anyone can use them. For example, you can check out my own package on GitHub. To install it, simply run:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;remotes::install_github(&amp;quot;mikenguyen13/mikenguyen&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feel free to use it for your research, whether you’re in marketing, science, or just a data enthusiast like me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, are you ready to dive into the world of R packages? Great! Let’s get started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;setting-up&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Setting Up&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First things first, we need to install a couple of packages that will make our lives easier: devtools and roxygen2. You can install them using the following commands:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;install.packages(&amp;quot;devtools&amp;quot;)
install.packages(&amp;quot;roxygen2&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;creating-the-framework-for-your-first-package&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Creating the Framework for Your First Package&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we have our tools, we can start building the framework for our package. We can do this using devtools:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;devtools::create(&amp;quot;myfirstpackage&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This command creates a folder with the same name as your package name and populates it with a few files. For now, we’ll focus on the DESCRIPTION file (where all the meta-data about your package goes) and the R folder (where all your R code goes).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, you can use the &lt;code&gt;usethis&lt;/code&gt; package. It should give you all the skeleton files you need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;usethis::create_package(&amp;quot;package_name&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this way won’t allow you to do it within a directory linked with github. You will have to manually make a git repo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;usethis::use_git()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;add-a-description-file&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Add a DESCRIPTION file&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;usethis::use_description()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you open this file, you will see it is pretty much self-explanatory&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;add-a-license&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Add a license&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many options for you to choose from. I typically just type &lt;code&gt;usethis::uselicense&lt;/code&gt; (I know this is incorrect; there is no such function, but R will suggest functions that are close in spelling). The most common license is GPL-3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;usethis::use_gpl3_license(&amp;quot;Mike Nguyen&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;adding-your-r-functions&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adding Your R Functions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All your R functions that you want in your R package belong in the R directory. You can create an .R file that has the same name as the function you want in it. For instance, let’s create a file called R/amatheme.R and add our function to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even easier, just use this function&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;usethis::use_r(&amp;quot;your_function&amp;quot;)
usethis::use_test(&amp;quot;your_function&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember to add the #’ @export tag above the function. This tag indicates that the function should be “exposed” to users to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s say we have a function &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;amatheme&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; that we want to include in our package. We would create a new .R file in the R directory of our package, let’s call it &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;amatheme.R&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. In this file, we would define our function:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;#&amp;#39; @export
amatheme &amp;lt;- function() {
  # Function body goes here
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;load-your-package&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Load Your Package&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To install and and load your package, you can simply&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(usethis)
library(devtools)
# don&amp;#39;t even need to specify your library
install()
library(&amp;quot;your_library&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;documenting-your-functions&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Documenting Your Functions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s talk about documentation. You know when you type ?amatheme in R and get that nice documentation? That’s what we’re going to do next. We can leverage off the roxygen2 package to document our functions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;usethis::use_roxygen_md()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To document our &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;amatheme&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; function, we would add special comments above the function definition in the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;amatheme.R&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;#&amp;#39; Title of the function
#&amp;#39;
#&amp;#39; @description A detailed description of what the function does.
#&amp;#39; @param param1 Description of the first parameter.
#&amp;#39; @param param2 Description of the second parameter.
#&amp;#39; @return Description of the return value.
#&amp;#39; @examples 
#&amp;#39; example1
#&amp;#39; example2
#&amp;#39; @export
amatheme &amp;lt;- function(param1, param2) {
  # Function body goes here
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve got your documentation completed, you can run &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;devtools::document()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to generate the .Rd files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;package-documentation&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Package Documentation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the key aspects of creating an R package is documentation. Good documentation is crucial for ensuring that others can understand and use your package. This includes not only commenting your code but also creating help files for each function and a detailed package vignette.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To create a vignette (i.e., tutorial) for our package, we would use the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;usethis::use_vignette(&#34;introduction&#34;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; function. This creates a template R Markdown file in the vignettes directory of our package. We can edit this file to provide a detailed introduction to our package.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A package vignette is a long-form guide that provides a comprehensive overview of your package. It typically includes an introduction to the package, detailed examples of how to use each function, and any other information that users might need to understand your package.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To install the vignette with the package&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;install(build_vignettes = T)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To see the vignette&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;vignette(&amp;quot;vignette_name&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;dependencies&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dependencies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When creating an R package, it’s important to carefully manage your package dependencies. These are other R packages that your package relies on. You should aim to minimize your dependencies to reduce the likelihood of conflicts and errors. When you do need to use other packages, make sure to specify them in the Imports field of your DESCRIPTION file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if our package depends on ggplot2, we would add the following line to the DESCRIPTION file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Imports:
  ggplot2&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;add-bells-and-whistles&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Add Bells and Whistles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;readme-file&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;ReadMe file&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, you’ve heard me blabber about creating your own package in R. But what if you don’t want to stop at just pushing it to your GitHub folder and hoping someone stumbles upon it during their 3 a.m. coding binge? What if you want to make it &lt;strong&gt;official&lt;/strong&gt;, put a badge on it, and show it off to the world like a proud pet owner?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s Start Simple&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;usethis::use_readme_md()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think of your README as the flashy storefront of your package. You wouldn’t walk into a store without a sign, right? (Unless you’re an adventurer, in which case, hats off to you!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The README should cover:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purpose:&lt;/strong&gt; Why did you make this? (And please don’t say “just because.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Installation:&lt;/strong&gt; We’re all eager beavers, but how do we get our paws on it?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Usage:&lt;/strong&gt; Once we have it, how do we use it without breaking our R session?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;add-a-pdf-manual&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Add A PDF Manual&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I always put the manual in the folder as my package so that I can sync it on GitHub&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;devtools::build_manual(path = getwd())
# alternatively you can do 
devtools::check(manual=TRUE)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;a-logo-because-even-r-packages-need-swag&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Logo: Because Even R Packages Need Swag&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did someone say branding? Just as you wouldn’t forget your grandmother’s face, you want people to remember your package. Create a chic logo that screams “I mean business... but in a fun, R-related way.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;use_logo()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;citation-give-credit-where-its-due&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Citation: Give Credit Where It’s Due&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If someone uses your package for their groundbreaking research and ends up winning a Nobel Prize, you want a slice of that credit pie (or at least a mention in the footnotes). Always provide a way for folks to cite your work. A little fame never hurt anybody!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;use_citation()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;badge-of-honor-the-bling-bling-for-your-package&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Badge of Honor: The Bling-Bling for Your Package&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;use_badge()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your package aced its tests? Has a 100% download rate by all three members of your family? Slap on a badge! It’s the jewelry of the coding world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;lifecycle-badge-is-your-package-a-baby-or-a-grandmaster&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lifecycle Badge: Is Your Package a Baby or a Grandmaster?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;use_lifecycle_badge()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let people know the maturity of your package. Is it experimental or stable? Is it questioning its place in the R universe? A lifecycle badge gives a quick glance into the evolutionary stage of your creation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;data&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to include raw data files (like .csv, .tsv, .txt, etc.) in your R package, you should place them in the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;inst/extdata&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; directory of your package. This is a standard location for storing raw data in R packages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s how you can use such data:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Add your raw data file to the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;inst/extdata&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; directory in your package. For example, you might add a file called &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;model-coef.rds&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;After installing your package, you can access the data file using the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;system.file()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; function. Here’s how you can do it:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;data_file_path &amp;lt;- system.file(&amp;quot;extdata&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;model-coef.rds&amp;quot;, package = &amp;quot;myfirstpackage&amp;quot;)
data &amp;lt;- readRDS(data_file_path)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this example, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;system.file()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; generates the full system path to the data file within the installed package. Then &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;readRDS()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is used to read the data into R.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember, the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;inst&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; directory in an R package is for “installed files” - these are files that are not R code or data, but which should be included with the package. The contents of the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;inst&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; directory are copied by R into the root of the package when it is installed, which is why you don’t include &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;inst&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; in the path when using &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;system.file()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;rules-of-thumb-and-industry-hacks&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rules of Thumb and Industry Hacks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few rules of thumb and industry hacks to keep in mind when creating your R package:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keep it simple:&lt;/strong&gt; Try to keep your package focused on one task or theme. This makes it easier for others to understand what your package does and how to use it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use meaningful function names:&lt;/strong&gt; Your function names should be descriptive and follow a consistent naming convention. This makes it easier for users to understand what each function does.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Test your package:&lt;/strong&gt; Make sure to thoroughly test your package before releasing it. This includes checking that all functions work as expected and that all documentation is clear and accurate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keep learning:&lt;/strong&gt; Creating an R package is a learning process. Don’t be afraid to make mistakes and keep improving your package over time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Alway remember to 
devtools::document()
usethis::use_test(&amp;quot;yournewfunction&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;put &lt;code&gt;export(yournewfunction)&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;import(needed_package)&lt;/code&gt; in NAMESPACE file&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;put the packages requirements under &lt;code&gt;Import:&lt;/code&gt; in DESCRIPTION file&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;put an example of the function in the Vignette file&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;installing-and-using-your-r-package&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Installing and Using Your R Package&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we’ve got our functions, we’ve got our documentation, what’s next? It’s time to install and use our package! We can use the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;devtools::install()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; function to install our R package into our R system library. Then we can load up our package with &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(&#34;myfirstpackage&#34;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;distributing-your-r-package&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Distributing Your R Package&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we’ve got our shiny new R package, how do we share it with the world? The easiest way is to distribute it through GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To distribute our package on GitHub, we first need to create a new repository on GitHub. Then, we can use Git to commit our package files and push them to the GitHub repository. Here’s an example of how to do this in the terminal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Navigate to the directory of your package
cd path/to/your/package

# Initialize a new Git repository
git init

# Add all files in the directory to the Git repository
git add .

# Commit the files
git commit -m &amp;quot;Initial commit&amp;quot;

# Add the GitHub repository as a remote
git remote add origin https://github.com/yourusername/yourrepository.git

# Push the files to the GitHub repository
git push -u origin master
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve pushed your package to GitHub, anyone can install it using the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;devtools::install_github(&amp;quot;yourusername/myfirstpackage&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To add a touch of academic flair to your distribution, why not submit it to a journal? Perhaps to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://joss.theoj.org/&#34;&gt;Journal of Open Source Software&lt;/a&gt; or the &lt;a href=&#34;https://openresearchsoftware.metajnl.com/articles&#34;&gt;Journal of Open Research Software&lt;/a&gt; (specifically for R is &lt;a href=&#34;https://journal.r-project.org/&#34;&gt;The R Journal&lt;/a&gt;). Personally, I’d give a thumbs up to The Journal of Open Source Software. Not only because I can spell it correctly, but also because they cozy up to your GitHub or ORCID account right off the bat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feeling even fancier? Consider creating a website to showcase all your vignettes. This not only provides a platform for your work but also allows you to monitor traffic and track visitors. For this, the pkgdown package is a splendid tool. It effortlessly transforms your R package documentation into a polished website, integrating your README, vignettes, function documentation, and other essential files to craft a cohesive online presence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setting up:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Install the pkgdown package if you haven&amp;#39;t already:
# install.packages(&amp;quot;pkgdown&amp;quot;, dependencies = TRUE)

# Build the website. Ensure you&amp;#39;re in your package directory:
pkgdown::build_site()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon execution, a &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;docs&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; directory will be generated, containing your website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Upload to GitHub&lt;/strong&gt;: Ensure you commit and push all updates, especially the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;docs&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; folder, to GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Activating GitHub Pages&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Navigate to your GitHub repository’s settings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under the “GitHub Pages” section, set the source to the master branch, specifically pointing to the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;/docs&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; folder.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accessing Your Site&lt;/strong&gt;: Your tailored package website is readily available at:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;https://&amp;lt;username&amp;gt;.github.io/&amp;lt;repository&amp;gt;/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that’s it! You’ve successfully created, documented, installed, and distributed your very own R package. But wait, there’s more! You can also check out my own package on GitHub. To install it, simply run:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;remotes::install_github(&amp;quot;mikenguyen13/mikenguyen&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feel free to use it for your research, whether you’re in marketing, science, or just a data enthusiast like me. Happy coding!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://undo.io/media/uploads/files/Code_for_six_minutes_meme.jpg&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; /&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.redd.it/m0xy5opltgm11.jpg&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>revert a commit</title>
      <link>https://mikenguyen.netlify.app/post/revert-a-commit/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mikenguyen.netlify.app/post/revert-a-commit/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://mikenguyen.netlify.app/post/revert-a-commit/index.en_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve recently committed a cardinal sin of pulling a merge without checking. And then, I had to try to revert back to my original commit. However, I also encounter an error saying &lt;code&gt;non-fast-forward&lt;/code&gt;. Hence, you have to do the following steps for a correct revert&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;git revert {commit_id}
git push origin -f&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After typing in your password, you should be reverted to the original state of the commit ID.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: To check your commit_id, on the right-hand side of Rstudio, you can see a clock next to the green up arrow. In the changes tab, you should see the column &lt;code&gt;SHA&lt;/code&gt;, which is the string of the commit id that you want to get.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Missing Git tab in Rstudio on Windows computer</title>
      <link>https://mikenguyen.netlify.app/post/missing-git-tab-in-rstudio-on-windows-computer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mikenguyen.netlify.app/post/missing-git-tab-in-rstudio-on-windows-computer/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://mikenguyen.netlify.app/post/missing-git-tab-in-rstudio-on-windows-computer/index.en_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Due to a new movement in the tech industry, organizations (e.g., companies or universities) will not allow their members to have complete control of their machines (i.e., administrative privileges or running programs as administrators). Hence, if members want to use this function, they typically have to apply for permission to use the “Make Me Admin” app, which grants administrator rights for 15 minutes. This movement can seriously hinder the working process and speed. But it seems unstoppable now (i.e., an industry-wide adoption). Hence, before installing programs on your computer, you will always need to run this app first. Or else, when being asked for admin privileges, your username and password will not suffice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, another movement is where organizations only use cloud storage (e.g., Dropbox, Box, OneDrive) instead of purchasing physical hard drives. Hence, your home default directory might be changed and cause unintended consequences (e.g., disintegration between GitHub and Rstudio). For example, my organization recently implemented an org-wide integration with OneDrive. Hence, my default home directory was changed from &lt;code&gt;C:\Users\tn9k4\Documents\&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;C:\Users\tn9k4\OneDrive - University of Missouri\Documents&lt;/code&gt;. This change disrupts my configuration between GitHub and Rstudio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can still manually push, pull, and do various things with GitHub, but only via manually coding. T&lt;strong&gt;he Git tab in Rstudio is missing in Rstudio on Windows computers.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I’ve tried to reinstall Git, Rstudio, and reset the Rstudio settings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I successfully cloned a repo from GitHub, but the tab would not appear.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And my terminal inside Rstudio looks like a normal Window Terminal (not like that of Git Terminal).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In my Global Options, my Git executable and SSH RSA key are working well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And none of the above solutions works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence, a manual modification is required to fix this hiccup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;First, we have to come back to the basics. We search for the Git on your machine. On Windows: &lt;code&gt;where git&lt;/code&gt; On Linux &amp;amp; Mac: &lt;code&gt;which git&lt;/code&gt; For me, I have three directories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;C:\Users\tn9k4\scoop\shims\git.exe&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;C:\Users\tn9k4\AppData\Local\Programs\Git\mingw64\bin\git.exe&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;C:\Users\tn9k4\AppData\Local\Programs\Git\cmd\git.exe&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Go to Tools -&amp;gt; Global Options -&amp;gt; Git/SVN, change the “Git executable” to the second path (&lt;code&gt;C:\Users\tn9k4\AppData\Local\Programs\Git\cmd\git.exe&lt;/code&gt;). The first is installed with Scoop, and your Rstudio cannot recognize it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Search on your Windows Search bar, “edit the system environment variables,” click on “Environment Variables”. Then click on “PATH” under the user variable (not the system variable). Add your bin path (e.g., &lt;code&gt;C:/Users/tn9k4/AppData/Local/Programs/Git/bin&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reset and Reopen your Rstudio; you should be able to see your Git tab now.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the problems stem from installing only to my user directory since I don’t have admin privileges yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To avoid these mambo jumbos, an alternative way is that you can simply uninstall git and scoop and reinstall Git with admin privileges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search for “Add or remove programs” in your Windows search bar. Then, uninstall “Git.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In “Terminal”, execute &lt;code&gt;scoop uninstall scoop&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then download Git 64 Standalone Installer from &lt;a href=&#34;https://git-scm.com/download/win&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://git-scm.com/download/win&lt;/a&gt; (use the version according to your computer). When opening the installer, right-click to “Run as Admin,” then you have the option to install it in &lt;code&gt;C:\Program Files\&lt;/code&gt; Remember to pick “Use Git from the Windows Command Prompt” and “Enable Symbolic Links.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open “Rstudio” with “Run as Admin”, go to Tools -&amp;gt; Global Options -&amp;gt; Terminal -&amp;gt; New terminal open with -&amp;gt; Select “Git Bash”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Voila! You are all set again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moral of the story: always “run as Admin” so that your system can consistently configure&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>remove files greater than 100MB from github repo before committing</title>
      <link>https://mikenguyen.netlify.app/post/remove-files-greater-than-100mb-from-github-repo-before-committing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mikenguyen.netlify.app/post/remove-files-greater-than-100mb-from-github-repo-before-committing/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://mikenguyen.netlify.app/post/remove-files-greater-than-100mb-from-github-repo-before-committing/index.en_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I accidentally commit files greater than 100 MB (which is against GitHub’s policy - only files less than 100MB). Hence, you should always either&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ignore the files by including their names in the &lt;code&gt;.gitignore&lt;/code&gt; files. You can either write the name of the file or use &lt;code&gt;*&lt;/code&gt; (e.g., &lt;code&gt;*.rds&lt;/code&gt; to ignore any files with &lt;code&gt;rds&lt;/code&gt; ending).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use &lt;a href=&#34;https://git-lfs.github.com/&#34;&gt;Git Large File Storage&lt;/a&gt; to store the files. This step is covered in &lt;a href=&#34;https://mikenguyen.netlify.app/post/upload-files-greater-than-100mb-to-github/&#34;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to our problems, how can we delete the wrong commits?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily we can use &lt;code&gt;bfg.jar&lt;/code&gt;, which could be downloaded from &lt;a href=&#34;https://rtyley.github.io/bfg-repo-cleaner/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I usually move the file to my GitHub directory that I want to use. But you can also leave it wherever you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To delete the wrong commits, you can either go to “Terminal”, or I usually just to the “Terminal” tab in RStudio. Then, you can type&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;java -jar bfg.jar --strip-blobs-bigger-than 100M &amp;lt;your_repo&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, I use&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;java -jar bfg-1.14.0.jar --strip-blobs-bigger-than 100M C:/Users/tn9k4/GitHub/finance&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where I have to change &lt;code&gt;bfg.jar&lt;/code&gt; because my file has its version in its name (or you can also change your &lt;code&gt;bfg.jar&lt;/code&gt; to match with your command) and my git repo is &lt;code&gt;C:/Users/tn9k4/GitHub/finance&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To find your git repo, you can also type in the “Terminal” tab&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;git rev-parse --show-toplevel&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please don’t include &lt;code&gt;.git&lt;/code&gt; in the repo location.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Upload files greater than 100MB to GitHub</title>
      <link>https://mikenguyen.netlify.app/post/upload-files-greater-than-100mb-to-github/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mikenguyen.netlify.app/post/upload-files-greater-than-100mb-to-github/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://mikenguyen.netlify.app/post/upload-files-greater-than-100mb-to-github/index.en_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What if you want to upload more than 100MB?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where &lt;a href=&#34;https://git-lfs.github.com/&#34;&gt;Git Large File Storage&lt;/a&gt; comes in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Step 1: After downloading it from the link above, type &lt;code&gt;git lfs isntall&lt;/code&gt; in your “Terminal” (once per user account)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Step 2: Go to the folder that has the files you want to upload, type this command&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;git lfs track &#34;*.rds&#34;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where you can &lt;code&gt;rds&lt;/code&gt; to any file types of your choice (e.g., mp4, jpeg, zip, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;if you want to commit multiple types then&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;git lfs track &#34;*.jpg&#34; &#34;*.png&#34; &#34;*.mp4&#34;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;my usual go-to command is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;git lfs track &#34;*.csv&#34; &#34;*.xlsx&#34; &#34;*.rds&#34; &#34;*.sas7bdat&#34; &#34;*csv.gz&#34; &#34;*.CSV&#34;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;which will create a &lt;code&gt;.gitattributes&lt;/code&gt; file&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;then, you need to track this file by&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;git add .gitattributes&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, you can also directly edit your &lt;code&gt;.gitattributes&lt;/code&gt; file (but then you still need to add it: &lt;code&gt;git add .gitattributes&lt;/code&gt; )&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, you are done. You can proceed to commit and push to GitHub like usual.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
